"Do the Health Benefits of
Peanut Butter Include Longevity?"
According to the largest study
of risk factors for death
in human history, a poor diet
causes more deaths than anything.
Cigarettes only kill about
eight million people a year,
whereas humanity’s diet
kills millions more.
What are the worst
aspects of our diet?
Processed meat? Twinkies? Soda?
No, the five deadliest
things about our diet are:
inadequate fruit intake—
not enough fruit;
not enough whole grains;
not enough vegetables;
too much salt; and not
enough nuts and seeds.
Nuts should come as no surprise
since interventional trials
have shown that eating nuts
improves artery function,
and arterial diseases
like heart disease are among
our leading killers. But
that’s not all nuts can do.
They may also improve
blood sugar control,
lower cholesterol, suppress inflammation,
reduce oxidative stress, and
feed our friendly gut flora.
All nuts or just tree nuts?
What about peanuts?
What about peanut butter?
About 50 percent of peanut
consumption in the U.S.
is through peanut butter,
but the association between
peanut butter and mortality
has not been
thoroughly evaluated. To get that
granular, though, we can call on
the NIH-AARP study, the
largest prospective health
and diet study in history
that followed more than
a half million people
since the 1990s.
And…nut consumption in
general appeared to protect
against all-cause mortality,
meaning nut-eaters live,
on average, longer lives, and
specifically, are less likely
to die from cancer, cardiovascular
disease, respiratory disease,
infectious causes (so, maybe
they help immunity as well),
liver disease, and kidney disease.
However, no such associations
were found for peanut butter.
So, when it comes to living longer,
peanut butter doesn’t
seem to count. Why?
Well, we know peanut butter
consumers tend to eat
more meat, smoke cigarettes,
and were less likely to exercise,
but the researchers
controlled for all that:
red meat, white meat, tobacco
use, exercise, and vegetables,
fruits, and whole grains;
so, it’s not like
the peanut butter eaters
were just eating more
white bread sandwiches or something.
The researchers didn’t
control for sugar though,
so it’s possible they could have
been eating more sugary jelly.
It could also be the
processing that goes into making
peanut butter—the added
transfat, oil, salt, and sugar—
but regular nuts
are also often eaten
with added oil, sugar, and salt.
Could it just be the
peanuts themselves?
Technically, they aren’t
nuts, so maybe they just
don’t have the same benefits.
But no, a meta-analysis
of all such studies found
the same nut-like benefits
for whole peanuts,
but just not peanut butter.
Well, one thing missing
from even no salt, oil-free,
sugar-free nut and seed butters
is intact cellular structure.
As I noted in How Not to Diet,
no matter how well we chew
whole or chopped nuts, some
of the nutrients remain trapped
in tiny particles that
deliver a bounty of
prebiotic goodness to
our friendly flora.
That makes me wonder if there
would have been any difference
between chunky and
smooth peanut butter.
In the meanwhile there is
compelling evidence to recommend
the use of nuts (preferably raw
nuts over salted or toasted)
and whole or chopped nuts
rather than nut butters,
at least three times a
week in order to maximize
your chances of living
longer and healthier lives.